Russel Wright Papers
Russel Wright Papers
1931-1965
Wright, Russel, 1904-1976.
60.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American industrial designer. Business records (1931-1964) pertaining to clients including American Cyanamid Corporation, Casein Company of America, Cornwall Corporation, and General Electric Company; architectural drawings, articles, lectures, book manuscripts, photographs, consumer and trade surveys, 1943-1959; clay, plaster, and paper models; and scrapbooks of clippings.
148767
Biographical History
"Good design is for everyone."
-- Russel Wright
Industrial designer Russel Wright (1904-1976) was born in Lebanon, Ohio. He attended local schools, studied at the Cincinnati Academy of Art (1921-1922), Columbia School of Architecture (1923), and New York University School of Architecture (1938-1939). (He also briefly studied law, at Princeton University, from 1922-1924.)
From 1924-1931 Wright was engaged in stage and costume design. He established his own factory in 1930 for the production of the first informal serving accessories. He became an industrial designer for well-known manufacturers in 1933, and in 1938 he designed "American Modern," the first contemporary dinnerware in America, for the Steubenville Pottery Company. He established his own design office in 1939, and that same year designed the first solid maple "blonde" modern furniture for the Conant Ball Company.
In 1940 he originated the "American Way" merchandising program, a cooperative undertaking of 65 designers, artists, craftsmen and manufacturers, and the following year "American Modern" received the American Designers' Institute award for the best ceramic design of 1941. In 1951 he received the Home Fashions League "Trail Blazer" award for upholstery fabric and table service.
With his wife, Mary Einstein, he co-authored A Guide to Easier Living, published by Simon and Schuster in 1951, which expressed their ideas for contemporary home living, maintenance, and furnishings. Together, they publicized Wright's designs and ideas through exhibitions, books, articles, advertisements, radio interviews, and demonstration rooms in department stores, creating a recognizable "brand name" and in effect inventing the idea of lifestyle marketing centered on an individual person. Ralph Lauren, Martha Stewart and other "household names" today are their conceptual descendants.
After his wife's death in 1952, Wright retired to Manitoga, his estate in Garrison, New York. Manitoga's 75 acres had been severely damaged by quarrying and logging, but Wright restored and renovated the area using native plants and created four miles of trails. On a portion of the land, with architect David Leavitt he designed and built Dragon Rock, a Japanese-inspired home and studio which, through its use of local materials, inhabits the landscape rather than dominating it. In 1996 Manitoga was listed on the National Register of Historic Places; it is also home to the Russel Wright Design Center, managed by Wright's daughter Annie, whose mission is "to preserve the legacy of pioneer designer Russel Wright-his home, landscape, products, archives and philosophy." [See the Manitoga web site.]
Wright was a founding fellow of the Society of Industrial Designers (later the Industrial Designers Society of America) and its president from 1951-1952.
Important dates in the life of Russel Wright
3 Apr 1904 Born in Lebanon, Ohio
1921-1922 Student under Frank Duveneck at the Cincinnati Academy of Art
1922-1924 Law student at Princeton University
1923 Student at Columbia School of Architecture
1924-1931 Engages in stage and costume design
1927 Marries Mary Einstein
1930 Establishes own facture for production of first metal informal serving accessories in New York City
1933 Becomes industrial designer for well-known manufacturers
1934 Invents "stove to table ware" of spun aluminum
1937 Designs "American Modern," the first contemporary dinnerware in America, for Steubenville Pottery (goes into production in 1939)
1938-1939 Student at New York University School of Architecture
1939 Opens own industrial design office; designs first solid maple "blonde" modern furniture for Conant Ball
1940 Begins "American Way" merchandising program
1941 "American Modern" receives American Designers' Institute award for best ceramic design of the year; purchases Manitoga estate in Garrison, New York
1950 Designs "Easier Living" line of furniture for the Statton Furniture Company of Hagerstown, Maryland; birth of daughter Annie
1951 Easier Living published by Simon and Schuster; receives Home Fashions League's "Trail Blazer" award for upholstery fabric and table design
1951-1952 President of Society of Industrial Designers
1952 Death of wife Mary
1954 Receives award from the Lebanon, Ohio, Chamber of Commerce
1956 Assigned by the International Cooperation Administration (ICA) to develop native handicrafts for local and export use in Cambodia, Taiwan and Vietnam
1955-1958 Serves as advisor on merchandising and selling in the wood and basketry industry in Japan
1956-1957 Construction begins on Dragon Rock, the 11-level home and studio Wright designed for his Manitoga property
1965 Wright closes his New York City office and retires to Manitoga
[Portions of this chronology adapted from Robert Stearns' essay, "Robert Wright: Living with Good Design."]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Russel Wright Papers consists of eight series and includes correspondence, business files and contracts relating to clients and products, writings, material related to Wright's work in Asia for the International Cooperation Administration (ICA), writings, memorabilia, and models of numerous Wright-designed items.
For the most part, Wright's own organization and labeling has been preserved, which means that material on a given company or project may be filed in more than one location. The researcher is advised to review the entire finding aid thoroughly to be sure of locating all relevant material.
Clients and products comprises the bulk of the collection and contains material relating to work done for clients (DuPont, Forster Textiles, General Electric, Hunt Foods, Iroquois China, National Silver, the New York World's Fair, Proctor and Gamble, Raymor Manufacturing, Shwayder Brothers, Statton Furniture, Sterling China, Steubenville, Wurlitzer Piano) as well as to particular items including but by no means limited to bedspreads, bottles, casseroles, cups, dog baskets, glassware, intaglio sets, jewelry, lamps, patents, plasticware, "rustic dinnerware," stove-to-tableware, and woodenware. Materials includes sketches, drawings, photographs, color and fabric samples, illustrations, renderings, catalogs, notes, layouts, and other items.
Writings contains a biographical sketch, galleys for Easier Living, manuals, and a large number of articles and lectures.
Correspondence/subject files includes many trade and popular publications as well as companies and a few individuals.
Surveys comprises surveys done on a range of subjects from "American brides" to "Home of tomorrow" to the Taiwan Handicraft Promotion Center.
Foreign activities contains material relating to Wright's work in numerous foreign countries (Asia and the far east, Dominican Republic, Puerto Rico), as well as with the ICA.
In Contracts will be found contracts and related material for clients, both corporate and individual.
Memorabilia includes clippings, manuscripts, notes, fabrics, and photographs, including material from Wright's own apartment.
Thirty-six boxes of Models -- clocks, cups, bowls, dishes, plates, pots and pans, serving plates, vases, and more -- complete the collection.
Note on missing items: Following items are known to be missing from the collection.
History of American Modern sources, Box 1
Item no. 1080 - Photomural of John Hull flatware. Package was sealed, item was listed in correspondence, but was not present in package.
Item no. 1086 - General Electric clocks. Package listed 10 items but only two were enclosed (no. 6-B, round ceramic clock, and another clock, possibly no. 3-B). Missing are:
4-A, straw front clock
3-B, transparent with green lines clock (possibly present)
7-B, round ceramic clock with white center
8-B, oval enamel steel clock
10-B, wood clock
11-B, wood veneer clock
12-B, wood veneer and plastic clock
13-A, perforated metal clock
14-B, metal and wood clock
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetically by name, title, or topic.
Note regarding negatives: Both processed sections of the Russel Wright Papers have a siginificant number of photographs (enlarged, 8x10" prints, clippings, and others), and some of these may contain negatives, either filed with the print(s) in the collection or stored in the finding aids file. If the researcher cannot find a negative copy of a photo from any of the boxes, or from a photo stored in the oversize packages (i.e. scrapbooks or enlarged prints), check with either the Manuscripts Librarian or other staff member as to whether any negatives may be stored elsewhere.
Related Material
holds the papers of a number of noted industrial designers, as well as the records of the
Industrial Design Society of America
. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Industrial Design; Wright, Russel, 1904-1976.; Industrial design -- United States.; Industrial designers -- United States.; Art and industry.; Architectural drawings (visual works); Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Collages (visual works); Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Lectures.; Manuscripts for publication.; Mock-ups.; Models (representations); Negatives (photographs); Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sketches.; Industrial designers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
The majority of the collection was gift of Russel Wright. There have been a very few additions from Ann Kerr (photographs and slides) and Diane Zumsteg (tableware from Staffordshire China, 3 photographs).
Inventory
- Clients and products
  - Accessories
    - Catalogues (Box 1)
    - Early, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Aluminum Goods Manufacturing (Box 1)
  - Alladin, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - American Crystal (Box 1)
    See also Oversize material: Miscellaneous design studies (Oversize 38).
  - American Cyanimid, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - American Modern
    - Book, See Oversize material: Miscellaneous (Oversize 6).
    - Clippings and ads, See Memorabilia: Scrapbooks: "American Modern" clippings (Oversize 40).
    - Child set; "Dec., Petunia" drawing (Box 1)
    - Dinnerware, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - History book of sources [MISSING 1975]
    - Press clippings, etc., See Memorabilia: Scrapbooks: "American Modern" clippings (Oversize 40).
    - Tablecloth designs, See Oversize material: Miscellaneous (Oversize 20).
  - American Way
    - Advertising, misc (Box 1)
    - Catalogs (Box 1)
    - Craft sketches (Box 1)
    - Design studies, aluminum, all around, cowboy modern, desks and bookcases (maple), desks and library tables, dinettes; 8 folders (Box 1)
    - Design studies, dining room, living room, maple, modern, odd chairs, Old Hickory (Box 90)
    - Design studies (Box 2)
    - Design studies (oversize), See Oversize material: Miscellaneous design studies (Oversize 38).
    - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Amtra Trading Company, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Amtra Trading House (Box 2)
  - Anchor Hocking Glass Corporation, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Appleman Art Glass, 10 folders (Box 2)
  - Art Loom Carpet Company
    - Rug presentation renderings (Oversize 33)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Associated merchandising
    - Plaster models (Box 2)
    - Working model (Box 2)
  - Baker - Lockwood, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Bartlett - Collins Company, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Bauer Pottery Company, 8 folders (Box 2)
  - Bedspread fabric (Box 2)
  - Bent Glass, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Better Homes and Gardens (Box 2)
  - Bloomingdale display rooms (Box 2)
  - Bottle storage (Box 2)
  - Bowes, 6 folders (Box 2, 3)
  - Bowl for soup, cereal, and dessert (Box 3)
  - Brass Rail Vending Restaurants
    - [General], 1962; 1964; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Back stamp (Box 3)
    - Canapé (Box 3)
    - Casserole (Box 3)
    - Casserole cover (Box 3)
    - Color samples (Box 3)
    - Color schemes (Box 3)
    - Color and texture samples (Box 3)
    - Conference (Box 3)
    - Covers for hot food (Box 3)
    - Covers for hot platters (Box 3)
    - Dish, dessert (Box 3)
    - Dish, pie (Box 3)
    - Draftings (Box 3)
    - Food screen research, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - General Electric restaurant (Box 3)
    - Grand Central City (Box 3)
    - Hot platter, early designs (Box 3)
    - Knife, fork, spoon (Box 3)
    - Lighting (Box 3)
    - Monograms (Box 3)
    - Napkins, salt and pepper, mustard cups (Box 3)
    - Patterns for cold cup (Box 3)
    - Respective drawings (Box 3)
    - Salad bowl (Box 3)
    - Screen vegetable (Box 3)
    - Signs for machines (Box 3)
    - Structural systems (Box 3)
    - Symbols (Box 3)
    - Trays (Box 3)
    - Vending line studies (Box 3)
    - Vending machine designs, See Oversize material: Miscellaneous (Oversize 23).
    - Vending machines
      - Aplo (Box 3)
      - Continental (Box 3)
      - Research (Box 3)
      - Rowe (Box 3)
      - Sanitation code (Box 3)
      - Vendo (Box 3)
      - Whittenborg (Box 3)
    - Vending restaurants (Box 3)
  - Brochures
    - All dinnerware lines (Box 3)
    - Russel Wright (Box 3)
  - Broil King (Box 3)
  - Broil Quick (Box 3)
    See also Peerless Electricity, Inc. as well as Oversize material: Miscellaneous (Oversize 16) and Oversize material: Miscellaneous (Oversize 18).
  - Buffet platter (Box 3)
  - Butter dishes (Box 4)
  - Calvert Distributing Company
    - [General], 1955 (Box 4)
    - Bottle design (Box 4)
    - Carton (Box 4)
    - Carton final drawings and artwork (Box 4)
    - Carton studies (Box 4)
    - Decanter (Box 4)
    - Drawings (Box 4)
    - Label, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Label final artwork (Box 4)
    - Notes, factory and sales (Box 4)
    - Notes and sketches (Box 4)
    - Pitchers, spouted (Box 4)
    - Presentation (Oversize 28)
    - Presentation sketches of 8 teardrop decanters (Box 4)
    - Printing samples (Box 4)
    - Reserve label and carton (Box 4)
    - Small decanter (Box 4)
  - Campbell Soup Company exhibit, World's Fair (Box 4)
  - Candles (Box 4)
  - Caribe Hilton Dinnerware decoration (Box 4)
  - Casein Company of America
    - [General], 1939-1940 (Box 4)
    - Cigarette box (Box 4)
    - Cart, tea (Box 4)
    - Final drawings (Box 4)
    - Lamps (Box 4)
    - Stanley Tool promotion (Box 4)
    - Tables
      - Card table (Box 4)
      - Coffee table (Box 4)
    - Trays
      - Bed tray (Box 4)
      - Hostess tray (Box 4)
    - Unit furniture (Box 4)
    - Unit pieces (Box 4)
    - Vanity (Box 4)
  - Casserole shapes and capacity (Box 4)
  - Casseroles and platters (Box 4)
  - Casual china (Box 4)
  - Century Craft
    - Accessory items (Box 4)
    - Bowls, punch (Box 4)
    - Candlesticks (Box 4)
    - Decanters (Box 4)
    - Decorated pieces (Box 4)
    - Drawings (Box 4)
    - Glasses (Box 4)
    - Ice buckets (Box 4)
    - Indiana Glass Company (Box 4)
    - Pitchers and cocktail mixers (Box 4)
  - Century Metalcraft Corporation, 1940-1944 (Box 4)
  - Chase Brass and Copper (Box 4)
  - Children's feeding service, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Classic Plastics color, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Clippings
    - Good ideas (Box 4)
    - Pretty kitchens (Box 4)
  - Colonial Metal Spinning and Stamping Company (Box 4)
  - Colonial source material collection (Box 5)
  - Competitors (Box 5)
  - Conant Ball Company renderings (Box 5)
  - Conant Ball Furniture / Christmas list (Box 5)
  - Concord Penthouse (Box 5)
  - Contact like materials (Box 5)
  - Cooper – Hewitt (Oversize 21)
  - Cornell (Box 5)
  - Cornwall Corporation
    - Dish, vegetable (Box 5)
    - Drawings (Box 5)
    - Drawings and prints (Box 5)
    - Label (Box 5)
    - Label research (Box 5)
    - Notes and research (Box 5)
    - Personal (Box 5)
    - Research (Box 5)
    - Sketches (Box 5)
    - Tray
      - Competitive material (Box 5)
      - Handle sketches (Box 5)
      - Pattern (Box 5)
      - Research (Box 5)
      - Thermo, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Well - tree
      - Drawings (Box 5)
      - Sketches (Box 5)
    - Vikon tile (Box 5)
  - Country Gardens dinnerware (Box 5)
  - Cowhide chair (Box 5)
  - Cowhide chair photos (Box 5)
  - Creamer and sugar bowl (Box 5)
  - Creamer and sugar studies (Box 5)
  - Cresca Company, Inc.
    - Color samples (Box 6)
    - Drafts (Box 6)
    - Drawings (Box 6)
    - Jar catalog (Box 6)
    - Labels
      - Layouts and paste-ups (Box 6)
      - Roughs (Box 6)
      - Final (Box 6)
      - Patterns (Box 6)
      - Research (Box 6)
      - Sketches (Box 6)
    - Logos (Box 6)
    - Party set (Box 6)
    - Studies, Christmas candle box (Box 6)
    - Studies, label (Box 6)
    - Studies, logo (Box 6)
  - Cup with new type handle (Box 6)
  - Defense Dept. housing (Box 6)
  - Diaper pail (Box 6)
  - Dinnerware (Box 6)
  - Dinnerware ideas
    - Unfinished, 8 folders (Box 6)
    - Unfinished theme 3 (Box 6)
    - Unfinished theme 10 (Box 6)
  - Dog baskets (Box 6)
  - DuPont
    - [General], 1952 (Box 7)
    - [General], 1956-1957 (Box 7)
    - Antique leather
      - [General], 1956-1957 (Box 7)
      - Palentia, 1956-1958 (Box 7)
    - Basket weave
      - Dorchester, 1955-1956 (Box 7)
      - Dorchester notes (Box 7)
    - Breathable finals (Box 7)
    - Cambodia
      - Fabril (Box 7)
      - Approved colors (Box 7)
      - Notes (Box 7)
    - Castleton (Box 7)
    - Castleton
      - Fabrilite samples (Box 7)
      - Folding door - prelims - colors (Box 7)
      - Research, RW (Box 7)
    - Chalk talk charts (Box 7)
    - Chalk talk charts, oversize (Oversize 32)
    - Cimarron (Box 7)
    - Clouds research (Box 7)
    - Color information inclusion program (Box 7)
    - Color notes (Box 7)
    - Color popularity research (Box 7)
    - Colors
      - Angola - Royola Tablet (Box 7)
      - Automobiles (Box 7)
      - Barony double (Box 7)
      - Cambodia (Box 7)
      - Castleton - interior (Box 7)
      - Preliminaries (Box 7)
      - Charcoal brown and cantaloupe, requests for (Box 7)
      - Cimarron (Box 7)
      - Cimarron strike offs (Box 8)
      - Cornwall (Box 8)
      - Tweed, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Tweed preliminary specification (Box 8)
      - Cracked ice (Box 8)
      - Crossmatch tweed (Box 8)
      - Double print (Box 8)
      - El Morro prelim series (Box 8)
      - Hammertone research (Box 8)
      - Leather office (Box 8)
      - Luggage - men (Box 8)
      - Paisley samples (Box 8)
      - Pigskin prelim. specifications (Box 8)
      - Prelim. test runs (Box 8)
      - Roanoke prelim. (Box 8)
      - School (Box 8)
      - Seville (kid leather) (Box 8)
      - Starfrost prelim. specs (Box 8)
    - Cornwall
      - Embossing, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Geometric (Box 9)
      - Patent photos and report (Box 9)
        See also Oversize material: Miscellaneous (Oversize 9).
    - Crosshatch research material (Box 9)
    - Dacron and Mylar samples (Box 9)
    - Double print strike offs (Box 9)
    - El Morro, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Experimental program
      - Fabric research samples (Box 9)
      - Fantasy (Box 9)
      - Fantasy design (also called "RW Topography") (Box 9)
      - File system (Box 9)
      - Floral (leaves) (Box 9)
      - Folding door (Box 9)
      - Hair design - Kramer - strike offs (Box 9)
      - Inclusion material - embossings (Box 9)
      - Leather embossing samples (Box 9)
    - Leather samples (Box 10)
    - Leopard samples (Box 10)
    - Linen 877 - luggage and case goods (Box 10)
    - Lost and found (Box 10)
    - Luggage - contact price via N.Y. office (Box 10)
    - Marble
      - Levant Morocco grain sample (Box 10)
      - Sample (Box 10)
      - 12 grain sample (Box 10)
    - Metalics - weave samples, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Montgomery hair cell
      - Embossing samples (Box 10)
      - Strike offs (Box 10)
      - Studies (Box 10)
    - Mylar polyester film (Box 10)
    - Notes and research (Box 10)
    - Paisley (Box 10)
    - Patent photos, See Oversize material: Miscellaneous (Oversize 4) and Oversize material: Miscellaneous (Oversize 9).
    - Pattern suggestions - showroom (Box 10)
    - Pattern suggestions - showroom (oversize) (Oversize 14)
    - Pebble effects (Box 10)
    - Photomicrograph studies (Box 10)
    - Pigskin experiments (Box 10)
    - Pigskin grain - antique print (Box 10)
    - Pigskin leather samples (Box 10)
    - Pigskin tests (Box 10)
    - Pigskin vinyl samples (Box 10)
    - Presentation, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Presentation calligraphy (Box 10)
    - Presentation, 1957
      - (Chinese) calligraphy research (Box 10)
      - Excelsior (Box 10)
      - Folders for color palettes (Box 10)
      - Linen (Box 10)
    - Presentation material
      - Hair no.3 (Box 11)
      - Moiré (Box 11)
      - Paisley (Box 11)
      - Pick up sticks (Box 11)
      - Rejects (Box 11)
      - Showroom (Box 11)
        See also Oversize material: Miscellaneous (Oversize 15).
    - Pyroxin (Box 11)
    - Reptile skin samples, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Rubber cement studies (Box 11)
    - Saddle leather samples (Box 11)
    - Sales research
      - Case goods coverings (Box 11)
      - Competition (Box 11)
      - Customer information (Box 11)
      - Furniture (Box 11)
      - Information from customers (Box 11)
    - Seville (kid leather) (Box 11)
    - Siam, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Sketches - rejected (Box 12)
    - Starfrost
      - Design (Box 12)
      - Notes (Box 12)
      - Samples (Box 12)
    - Strawhat texture (Box 12)
    - Sumatra (Box 12)
    - Tapelle (Box 12)
    - Technical notes
      - Design program (Box 12)
      - Newburgh (Box 12)
      - Roehlin (Box 12)
    - Textures (Box 12)
    - Textures research (Box 12)
    - Unused patterns (Box 12)
    - Unused patterns (oversize), See Oversize material: Miscellaneous (Oversize 12).
    - Weave samples (Box 12)
    - Weaves
      - Rollen engravings (Box 12)
      - Straw samples (Box 12)
      - Wood samples (Box 12)
  - Durelle restaurant (Box 12)
  - Easy Living Lamps (Box 12)
  - Eaton's (Box 12)
  - Edison, Inc.
    - Prints (Oversize 2)
  - Englishtown Cutlery, Ltd.
    - Bolster (Box 12)
    - Colors (Box 12)
    - Cutlery (Box 12)
    - Cutlery Ltd. Sample drawings (Box 12)
    - Cutlery silverware renderings (Box 12)
    - Experiments (Box 12)
    - Extruded (Box 12)
    - Flatware (Box 12)
    - Museum sketches (Box 12)
    - Non bolster (Box 12)
    - Plastic handled, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Renderings, See Oversize material: Miscellaneous (Oversize 16).
    - Research correspondence (Box 12)
    - Roughs and finals (Box 12)
    - Selected sketches (Box 12)
    - Silverware adds (Box 12)
    - Spun glass (Box 12)
    - Tracings
      - All steel (Box 12)
      - Plastic handle (Box 12)
  - Fairmount Lamps
    - General, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - Competitors, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Data (Box 13)
    - Design for presentation (Box 13)
    - Final drawings (Box 13)
    - Material sources (Box 13)
    - New ideas (Box 13)
    - Shade data (Box 13)
    - Stock material (Box 13)
    - Studies and tracings (Box 13)
    - Switch cap cover (Box 13)
    - Switch cover (Box 13)
    - Unused designs (Box 13)
  - Familyware
    - Colors (Box 13)
    - Lists of pieces (Box 13)
    - Market study (Box 13)
    - Stacking salt and pepper (Box 13)
    - Template drawings (Box 13)
    - Two compartment vegetable server (Box 13)
  - Forster Fabrics (Box 13)
  - Forster Textiles
    - Color studio samples (Box 13)